Guide to the Edward Eberstadt & Sons Records
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Edward Eberstadt & Sons records
1910-1954
WA MSS S-2698
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
13.82
(40 boxes)
The records document the business activity of Edward Eberstadt and include records from three of his firms: Hudson Book Company, Edward Eberstadt, and Edward Eberstadt & Sons. While some material dates to Eberstadt's early years in business, most of the collection documents Eberstadt's business relationship with William Robertson Coe (Eberstadt was Coe's agent), and the formation of the Coe Collection of Western Americana. Records include financial records, acquisition records, correspondence between Eberstadt and Coe and between Eberstadt and other dealers, and descriptions of rare books and manuscripts, including some transcripts of manuscripts.
Edward Eberstadt & Sons
Related Materials
Thomas W. Streeter collection of Hudson Book Company, Edward Eberstadt, and Edward Eberstadt & Sons catalogs (WA MSS S-2588). Yale Collection of Western Americana, Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Edward Eberstadt, 1959, and of Charles F. Eberstadt, 1974.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Edward Eberstadt & Sons
Edward Eberstadt & Sons was a bookselling business in New York City, specializing in rare books and manuscripts related to the history of the American West. The business was started by Edward Eberstadt (1883-1958) as The Latin American Book Company, and later the Hudson Book Company in Tarrytown, NY, circa 1910, specializing in Latin Americana. The business later became Edward Eberstadt and, finally, Edward Eberstadt & Sons. Edward's sons Charles and Lindley Eberstadt joined the firm in the late 1930s and continued the business until Charles's death in 1974 and Lindley's death in 1985.
William Robertson Coe (1869-1955)
William Robertson Coe was born in Staffordshire, England, and immigrated to Pennsylvania at the age of 14. He began working in the insurance business soon thereafter, and by 1910 had risen to become the president of Johnson and Higgins Insurance Co. He was among the foremost collectors of Western Americana in the early twentieth century, and his gifts of rare books and manuscripts became the foundation of the Yale Collection of Western Americana at the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library.
Scope and Contents
The records document the business activity of Edward Eberstadt and include records from three of his firms: Hudson Book Company, Edward Eberstadt, and Edward Eberstadt & Sons. While some material dates to Eberstadt's early years in business, most of the collection documents Eberstadt's business relationship with William Robertson Coe (Eberstadt was Coe's agent), and the formation of the Coe Collection of Western Americana, which was donated to Yale in the 1940s. Records include financial records, acquisition records, correspondence between Eberstadt and Coe and between Eberstadt and other dealers, and descriptions of rare books and manuscripts, including some transcripts of manuscripts.
Arrangement
Organized into six series: I. Financial Records, 1910-1945. II. Correspondence, 1920-1954. III. Appraisal Records, 1943-1953. IV. Acquisition Files, circa 1920-circa 1950. V. Catalog Files, 1942-1951, undated. VI. Other Papers, 1930-1945.
Acquisition of manuscripts -- United States; Antiquarian booksellers -- United States; Book auctions -- United States; Book collecting -- United States; Book collectors -- United States; Book industries and trade -- United States; Books -- Prices; Booksellers and bookselling -- United States; Bookstores -- United States; Cataloging of manuscripts -- United States; Libraries and booksellers -- United States; Manuscripts, American -- United States; Rare books -- United States; West (U.S.) -- Bibliography; Antiquarian booksellers; Book collectors -- United States; Coe, William Robertson, 1869-1955; Eberstadt, Charles F. (Charles Francis), 1912-1974; Eberstadt, Edward, 1883-1958; Eberstadt, Lindley; Edward Eberstadt (Firm); Edward Eberstadt & Sons; Hudson Book Company; Yale Collection of Western Americana
- Financial Records, 1910-1945; Series I; 0.84; (7 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Organized into two subseries: Accounting Records and Coe Collection Bills.
  Scope and Contents
  Series I consists of records relating to the purchase of rare books and manuscripts, and to business expenses, and bills to William R. Coe for acquisitions on his behalf.
  - Accounting Records, (6 volumes and 1 folder)
    Arranged roughly chronologically.
    - Account book, 1908 (Box 1)
    - Account book, 1910-1915 (Box 2)
    - Account book, 1910-1913 (Box 3)
    - Account book, 1911-1916 (Box 4)
    - Account book, 1917-1920 (Box 5)
    - Account book, 1914-1916 (Box 6)
    - "Purchases by Hudson Book Company", 1920 (Box 7)
  - Coe Collection Bills
    - Bills, 1920-1928; 2 (Box 7)
    - Bills, 1920-1934; 2 (Box 7)
    - Bills, 1936-1945 (Box 7)
    - Bills, 1937-1939 (Box 7)
    - Bills, 1940-1941 (Box 7)
    - Bills, 1944 (Box 7)
- Correspondence, 1920-1954; Series II; 1.88; (5 boxes)
  Organized into two subseries: General Correspondence (Chronological) and General Correspondence (Alphabetical).
  Series II consists of Edward Eberstadt's business correspondence, incoming and retained outgoing copies. Much of the correspondence is between Eberstadt and William R. Coe, or relates to acquisitions for the Coe collection. A small amount of William R. Coe's correspondence (letters to and from people other than Eberstadt) is interfiled.
  - General Correspondence (Chronological)
    - General correspondence, 1920-1921; 3 (Box 8)
    - General correspondence, 1921-1922 (Box 8)
    - General correspondence, 1921-1930 (Box 8)
    - General correspondence, 1923-1932 (Box 8)
    - General correspondence, 1923-1945 (Box 9)
    - General correspondence, 1925-1937 (Box 9)
    - General correspondence, 1930s (Box 9)
    - General correspondence, 1932-1940 (Box 9)
    - General correspondence, 1932-1943 (Box 9)
    - General correspondence, 1934-1938 (Box 9)
    - General correspondence, 1937 (Box 9)
    - General correspondence, 1939 (Box 9)
    - General correspondence, 1940 (Box 9)
    - General correspondence, 1943-1948 (Box 10)
    - General correspondence, 1943-1952 (Box 10)
    - General correspondence, 1943-1953 (Box 10)
    - General correspondence, 1945 (Box 10)
    - General correspondence, 1945-1950 (Box 10)
    - General correspondence, 1945-1951 (Box 10)
    - General correspondence, 1949-1950 (Box 10)
    - General correspondence, 1951 (Box 10)
    - General correspondence, 1952 (Box 11)
    - General correspondence, 1952-1954 (Box 11)
    - General correspondence, 1953 (Box 11)
    - General correspondence, 1954-1955 (Box 11)
  - General Correspondence (Alphabetical)
    - "Birds", 1948-1952 (Box 11)
    - Buffalo Bill Museum Association, 1931-1939 (Box 11)
    - Crocker, Charles Templeton, 1921 (Box 11)
    - Hanna, Archibald, 1960-1967 (Box 11)
    - Holliday, Jim, 1952 (Box 11)
    - Yale University, 1944-1945 (Box 11)
    - Yale University, 1948-1949; 2 (Box 12)
- Appraisal Records, 1943-1953; Series III; 4.8; (12 boxes)
  Organized into two subseries: Coe Collection of Western Americana and Other Appraisal Records.
  Series III consists of descriptions and monetary appraisals of material in the Coe Collection, chiefly at the time of donation of the material to Yale University.
  - Coe Collection of Western Americana
    Organized under two headings: Drafts and Completed Volumes.
    - Drafts
      Arranged chronologically.
      - "Volume I: Manuscripts," draft, 1943; 4 (Box 13)
      - "Volume I," draft, 1944; 3 (Box 14)
      - "Volume II," draft, 1944; 2 (Box 14)
      - "Volume III," draft, 1944; 3 (Box 15)
      - "Volume I," draft, 1945; 3 (Box 15)
      - "Volume II," draft, 1945; 3 (Box 16)
      - "Volume III," draft, 1945; 3 (Box 16)
      - "Volume I," draft, 1946; 3 (Box 17)
      - "Volume II," draft, 1946; 3 (Box 17)
      - "Volume III," draft, 1946; 3 (Box 17)
      - "Volume I," draft, 1947; 3 (Box 18)
      - "Volume II," draft, 1947; 2 (Box 18)
      - "Volume II," draft, 1947 (Box 18)
    - Completed Volumes
      - Volume 1, Original Manuscript, 1943 (Box 19)
      - Volume II, Historical Works, 1944 (Box 19)
      - Volume III, Historical Works, 1944 (Box 19)
      - Volume IV, Plains and Rockies, Idaho, and British Columbia Imprints, 1945 (Box 20)
      - Volume V, Plains and Rockies, Idaho, and British Columbia Imprints, 1945 (Box 20)
      - Volume VI, Plains and Rockies, Idaho, and British Columbia Imprints, 1945 (Box 20)
      - Volume VII, Historical Works, 1946 (Box 21)
      - Volume VIII, Historical Works, 1946 (Box 21)
      - Volume IX, Historical Works, 1946 (Box 22)
      - Volume X, Historical Works, 1947 (Box 22)
      - Volume XI, Historical Works, 1947 (Box 22)
      - Western Americana (no volume number), 1949 (Box 23)
      - Volume XIII, Historical Works, 1951 (Box 23)
      - Historical Works (no volume number), 1952-1953 (Box 23)
  - Other appraisal records
    - Appraisal records, 1944-1966, undated; 3 (Box 24)
    - Ed Lazare appraisal records, 1951-1952; 3 (Box 24)
    - Notes, including appraisal records, 1952 (Box 24)
    - Records of gifts, 1953, undated; 2 (Box 24)
- Acquisition Files, circa 1920-circa 1950; Series IV; 2.92; (7 boxes)
  Series IV consists of files that document the purchase and sale of material by Edward Eberstadt's firms, as well as research carried out by employees. Files often include transcripts of manuscripts. Dates have not been supplied for the files, reflecting the fact that they are undated and may have been compiled or revised over time.
  Arranged alphabetically by author, subject or other main entry.
  - Anderson, William Marshall, 2 (Box 25)
  - Astor, John Jacob (Box 25)
  - Audubon, _____ (Box 25)
  - Ball, John (Box 25)
  - Barnes, James S. (Box 25)
  - Belden, Josiah (Box 25)
  - Bell, Josias Fendall (Box 25)
  - Bierce, Ambrose (Box 25)
  - Bordman, Philip(?) (Box 25)
  - Brown, David L., 2 (Box 25)
  - Brown, Joseph W. (Box 26)
  - Bryant, Edwin and J. Quinn Thornton (Box 26)
  - Burch, John Chilton (Box 26)
  - Campbell, Robert (Box 26)
  - Clark, Major Meriwether Lewis (Box 26)
  - Clover, Isaac M. (Box 26)
  - Colgate, J.C. (Box 26)
  - Colgrow, David (Box 26)
  - Comfort, Aaron Ivins (Box 26)
  - Coon, Homer (Box 26)
  - Crooks, Ramsey (Box 26)
  - Crump, R.P. (Box 26)
  - Davidson, William Mitchell (Box 26)
  - Dellenbaugh, Frederick S. (Box 26)
  - Dowdon, Richard (Box 26)
  - Dunbar, William
  - Ellsworth, Henry L. (Box 26)
  - Emmons, George F. (Box 26)
  - English, W.L. (Box 26)
  - Estados Unidos Mexicanos (Box 26)
  - Everts, F.D. (Box 27)
  - Freeman, Henry (Box 27)
  - Gee, Perry (Box 27)
  - Green, George W. (Box 27)
  - Haller, Granville O. (Box 27)
  - Holts, _____
  - Hosmer, John Allen (Box 27)
  - Ingalls, Eleaser S. (Box 27)
  - Jackson, Alonzo C., 3 (Box 27)
  - Jacobson, _____ (Box 27)
  - Johnson Family (Box 27)
  - Johnson, George A. (Box 28)
  - Jones, Evan O. (Box 28)
  - Kingsbury, James M. (Box 28)
  - Lathrop, George (Box 28)
  - Lewis, Meriwether and William Clark, 2 (Box 28)
  - Lincoln, Abraham, 2 (Box 28)
  - MacKinlay, James (Box 28)
  - Mann, Stephen H. (Box 28)
  - Meetch, J.B. (Box 28)
  - National Atlas and Tuesday Morning Mail (Box 28)
  - Nez Perces, 2 (Box 28)
  - Pike, Z.M. (Box 28)
  - "Overland Fakes" (Box 28)
  - Pittman, Anna Maria (Box 29)
  - Reed, Gardner K. (Box 29)
  - Rothwell, William R. (Box 29)
  - Saint Joseph Gazette (Box 29)
  - Sharp, Thomas C. (Box 29)
  - Shuart, Jesse H., 2 (Box 29)
  - Shunk, William Findlay (Box 30)
  - Sinclair, James (Box 30)
  - Smith, Emma (Box 30)
  - Smith, Joseph (Box 30)
  - Strachan, John, 2 (Box 30)
  - Stuart, James Ewell Brown (Box 30)
  - Stuart, Robert (Box 30)
  - Sully, Alfred (Box 30)
  - Tiffany, P.C. (Box 31)
  - Walker, J.G. (Box 31)
  - Wickliffe, Charles A. (Box 31)
  - Unidentified, 6 (Box 31)
- Catalog Files, 1942-1951, undated; Series V; 2.92; (7 boxes)
  Not arranged in any particular order.
  Series V consists of catalog cards and slips documenting the Coe Collection and containing descriptions of material, bibliographic information, and prices.
  - "Mss cat", 1942 (Box 32)
  - "Coe catalog slips", undated (Box 32)
  - Wyoming catalog, 1951 (Box 32)
  - Catalog files, undated (Box 32)
  - Catalog cards, undated (Box 33)
  - Catalog cards, undated (Box 34)
  - Catalog cards, undated (Box 35)
  - Catalog cards, undated (Box 36)
  - Catalog cards, undated (Box 37)
  - Catalog cards, undated (Box 38)
- Other Papers, 1930-1945, undated; Series VI; 0.21; (1 box)
  Series VI consists of drafts of writings by Edward and Charles Eberstadt, and unsorted business papers, consisting chiefly of notes.
  - "The Brothers Nine," by Edward Eberstadt, drafts, 1945 (Box 39, Folder #1)
  - "On Colorado Guidebooks of '59," by Charles Eberstadt, draft, undated (Box 39, Folder #1)
  - Unsorted papers, 1930-1940, undated (Box 39, Folder #3)
- Oversize Material, 0.25; (1 box)
  - Dunbar, William (Series IV) (Box 40, Folder #1)
  - Holts, _____ (Series IV) (Box 40, Folder #1)